A Guide to the Kathryn H. Stone Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10555-a
Kathryn H. Stone Papers ca. 1881-1988
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10555-a
ca. 13,500 items
Kathryn H. Stone
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Mrs. Kathryn H. Stone of Alexandria, Virginia
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of Kathryn H. Stone, ca. 1881(1921-1965)1988, of ca. 13,500 items, pertains to Mrs. Stone's service in the General Assembly of Virginia, her involvement in the League of Women Voters, her work in the planning of Reston, Virginia, and various topics of interest or concern including civil rights, desegregation, education, health, and women's issues. There are correspondence, papers, reports, newspaper clippings and other printed material, photographs, and bound volumes. Some of the "topics of interest" consist chiefly of, but are not limited to, newspaper clippings; there are also letters from constituents and legislators, official reports and resolutions, speeches, and other papers, representing her activities in support of particular concerns. Material on Afro-American issues may be found under various headings such as "Desegregation," "J. Lindsay Almond, Jr.: Massive Resistance," "Leon Dure," "Gray Commission," and "National Association for the Advancement of Colored People," among others.
Container List
- Topical
  - Afro-Americans, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Agriculture, 1959 (Box Box 1)
  - Alexandria Schools, 1946-1965 (Box Box 1)
  - J. Lindsay Almond, Jr.: Budget, 1960 (Box Box 1)
  - J. Lindsay Almond, Jr.: General, 1959-1960 (Box Box 1)
  - J. Lindsay Almond, Jr.: Massive Resistance, 1959 (Box Box 1)
  - J. Lindsay Almond, Jr.: "What he didn't do", 1956-1959 (Box Box 1)
  - Arlington County Board, 1957-1958, 1975 (Box Box 1)
  - Arlington County Government, 1959-1964 (Box Box 1)
  - Arlington County: Segregation, 1960 (Box Box 1)
  - Arlington School Board, 1952-1960 (Box Box 1)
  - Arlingtonians for a Better Community, 1958 (Box Box 1)
  - American Association of University Women, 1960 (Box Box 2)
  - Bi-Racial Commissions, 1960 (Box Box 2)
  - Pearl S. Buck, 1960 (Box Box 2)
  - Budget-- Virginia, 1960 (Box Box 2)
  - Harry Flood Byrd, Sr. and The Byrd Machine, 1957-1961 (Box Box 2)
  - "The Byrd Machine: Survival Capacity of a Political Museum Piece" by M. Crawford Young, 1961 (Box Box 2)
  - Ann Perkins Cabell, 1958-1960 (Box Box 2)
  - Campaign Analysis, [1952] (Box Box 2)
  - Campaign Expenses, 1963 (Box Box 2)
  - Campaign Issues, 1954-1957 (Box Box 2)
  - Capital Punishment, 1957-1960 (Box Box 2)
  - Elsie Carper: "Virginia Affairs" and other articles, 1959-1960 (Box Box 2)
  - "Changes in Living Patterns" by Louisa Jane Harper, 1961 (Box Box 2)
  - Churches and Race, 1956-1960 (Box Box 2)
  - Civil Liberties, 1957-1958 (Box Box 2)
  - Civil Rights, 1956-1965 (Box Box 3)
  - Civil Rights: Newspaper Clippings, 1956-1960; (2 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Civil Rights Commission, 1957-1964 (Box Box 3)
  - Compulsory School Attendance, 1959 (Box Box 3)
  - Conflict of Interest, 1964 (Box Box 3)
  - Consortium for Continuing Higher Education in Northern Virginia, 1978-1980; (2 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Council on Human Relations, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  - Council of State Governments, 1959-1960 (Box Box 3)
  - Virginius Dabney, 1955-1960 (Box Box 3)
  - Democracy, 1940-1963 (Box Box 3)
  - Democratic Party, 1932-1969 (Box Box 4)
  - Desegregation, 1954-1959; (6 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - Desegregation, 1960-1962, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 5)
  - Desegregation: Supreme Court Decisions, 1954 (Box Box 5)
  - Leon Dure, 1958-1960 (Box Box 5)
  - Economics, 1960 (Box Box 5)
  - Education, 1958-1964 (Box Box 5)
  - Education: Newspaper Clippings, 1955-1965 (Box Box 5)
  - Education: Virginia General Assembly, 1959-1962 (Box Box 5)
  - Employment Commission, 1960 (Box Box 6)
  - Federal Courts, 1958-1960 (Box Box 6)
  - Marshall Fishwick, 1959-1960 (Box Box 6)
  - Foreign Policy, 1958-1959 (Box Box 6)
  - Max Freedman, 1959 (Box Box 6)
  - Freedom Event, 1958 (Box Box 6)
  - Joseph H. Freehill, 1958 (Box Box 6)
  - Future Homemakers of America, 1960 (Box Box 6)
  - General Assembly, 1950-1958; (5 folders) (Box Box 6)
  - General Assembly, 1959-1965, n.d.; (6 folders) (Box Box 7)
  - General Elections, 1957 (Box Box 7)
  - Germany, 1958-1959 (Box Box 7)
  - Howard C. Gilmer, Jr., 1957 (Box Box 7)
  - Government and Politics, 1958-1969 (Box Box 7)
  - Gray Commission, 1954-1959, n.d.; (5 folders) (Box Box 8)
  - Gray Commission: Newspaper Clippings, 1955-1959 (Box Box 8)
  - Albertis S. Harrison, Jr. vs. Sidney C. Day, Jr., 1959-1960 (Box Box 8)
  - Health and Welfare, 1957-1965 (Box Box 8)
  - James Howard Hershman, Jr., 1981-1985 (Box Box 8)
  - Housing, 1959-1960 (Box Box 8)
  - "Human Resources: Focus for the Sixties" by Kathryn H. Stone, ca. 1964 (Box Box 9)
  - Hunger, 1983-1986 (Box Box 9)
  - Industry, 1958-1960 (Box Box 9)
  - John Birch Society, 1963 (Box Box 9)
  - Juveniles, 1955-1964, n.d. (Box Box 9)
  - Martin Luther King, 1960 (Box Box 9)
  - Ku Klux Klan, ca. 1958-1960 (Box Box 9)
  - Letters re Kathryn H. Stone's Retirement from the House of Delegates, 1965 (Box Box 9)
  - Letters to Kathryn H. Stone re incident in the General Assembly involving Frank Moncure, 1958; (2 folders) (Box Box 9)
  - Little Rock, Arkansas, 1958-1960 (Box Box 9)
  - Lists--Memberships, Mailings, 1966-1979 (Box Box 9)
  - Harrison Mann, 1959 (Box Box 9)
  - Minimum Wage, 1960-1965 (Box Box 9)
  - Benjamin Muse, 1957-1959 (Box Box 9)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People( NAACP): Anti-NAACP, 1956-1965 (Box Box 10)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People( NAACP): Newspaper Clippings, 1955-1960 (Box Box 10)
  - National Civil Service League, 1963-1980; (3 folders) (Box Box 10)
  - National Civil Service League: Annual Report, 1976 (Box Box 10)
  - National Committee on Atomic Information: "Education for Survival" by Paul A. Beighley, 1969 (Box Box 10)
  - National Urban League, 1960 (Box Box 10)
  - Mary Cushing Niles, 1959-1963 (Box Box 10)
  - Norfolk, Virginia, 1959 (Box Box 10)
  - Northern Virginia, 1957-1960 (Box Box 11)
  - Northern Virginia Technical College, 1964-1968 (Box Box 11)
  - Oral History Interviews with Harold A. and Kathryn H. Stone, 1984-1985 (Box Box 11)
  - Parent Teacher Association, 1959-1960 (Box Box 11)
  - Pari-Mutuel Betting, 1958 (Box Box 11)
  - Peaceful Demonstrations, 1960-1961 (Box Box 11)
  - Planning, 1959-1960 (Box Box 12)
  - Poems, n.d. (Box Box 12)
  - Polio, 1959 (Box Box 12)
  - Poll Tax, 1959-1964 (Box Box 12)
  - Pollard Advisory Referendum, 1959, n.d. (Box Box 12)
  - Population Problems including Birth Control, 1959, n.d. (Box Box 12)
  - Francis Gary Powers, 1960 (Box Box 12)
  - Precinct Organization, 1952-1961, n.d. (Box Box 12)
  - Primary 1959, 1956-1964 (Box Box 12)
  - Prince Edward County, 1955-1965 (Box Box 12)
  - Private Schools, 1959-1960 (Box Box 12)
  - Pupil Placement Board, 1956-1960 (Box Box 13)
  - Quotations and Notes of Kathryn H. Stone, 1957-1959, n.d. (Box Box 13)
  - Racial Matters, 1955-1965 (Box Box 13)
  - Reapportionment, 1961-1965, n.d. (Box Box 13)
  - Reapportionment: Newspaper Clippings, 1959-1964 (Box Box 13)
  - Registration Bill, 1958 (Box Box 13)
  - Religion, 1959-1960 (Box Box 13)
  - Republicans in Virginia, 1958 (Box Box 13)
  - Roads, 1958-1959 (Box Box 13)
  - Eleanor Roosevelt, 1960 (Box Box 13)
  - School of Social Work, Virginia Commonwealth University, 1968(1976-1979) (Box Box 13)
  - David Scull, 1957-1958 (Box Box 13)
  - Eric Sevareid, 1960 (Box Box 13)
  - Social Legislation Information Service, 1960 (Box Box 13)
  - The South (General), 1959, 1960 (Box Box 13)
  - Southern Regional Council, 1959 (Box Box 13)
  - Speeches by Kathryn H. Stone, 1945-1965 (Box Box 14)
  - States' Rights: Fourteenth Amendment, Interposition, 1956-1963; (2 folders) (Box Box 14)
  - Adlai Stevenson, 1956-1960 (Box Box 14)
  - Kathryn H. Stone, 1945-1977, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 14)
  - Kathryn H. Stone: Photographs, 1950s, n.d. (Box Box 15)
  - Sunday Closings, 1959 (Box Box 15)
  - Tenth District Women's Democratic Club, 1958-1959 (Box Box 15)
  - Tuition Grants, 1959-1960 (Box Box 15)
  - University of Virginia: Northern Virginia Extension, 1958 (Box Box 15)
  - Virginia Advisory Legislative Council, 1959-1960 (Box Box 15)
  - Virginia Committee for Public Schools, 1955-1960, n.d. (Box Box 15)
  - Virginia Council on State Legislation, 1959 (Box Box 15)
  - Virginia Declaration of Rights: Letters of Appreciation, 1966 (Box Box 15)
  - Virginia Education Association, 1959 (Box Box 15)
  - Virginia Schools: Budget, 1959 (Box Box 15)
  - Warren County, 1959 (Box Box 15)
  - Robert Whitehead, 1957 (Box Box 15)
  - Women's Issues, 1922-1987 (Box Box 15)
  - Women's Affairs in Germany, 1955-1958 (Box Box 15)
- League of Women Voters
  - League of Women Voters, 1921-1933; (6 folders) (Box Box 16)
  - League of Women Voters, 1934-1939; (7 folders) (Box Box 17)
  - League of Women Voters, 1940-1947; (7 folders) (Box Box 18)
  - League of Women Voters, 1947-1949; (7 folders) (Box Box 19)
  - League of Women Voters, 1949-1980; (4 folders) (Box Box 20)
- Reston
  - Reston: The Beginnings: from the Bowman brothers to Robert E. Sims, Jr., n.d. (Box Box 20)
  - Reston: The Good Life in Reston: Cultural and Recreational Opportunities for Leisure by Jane Gilmer Wilhelm, and related (Box Box 20)
  - Reston: Housing Conference Transcripts, n.d. (Box Box 20)
  - Reston: A Study of Beginnings by Kathryn H. Stone, 1966, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 21)
  - Reston: A Study of Beginnings, Vol. II, Appendix, 1966 (Box Box 21)
  - Reston: Brochures, 1965-1969; (2 folders) (Box Box 21)
  - Reston: Development and Planning--Miscellaneous, 1962-1965 (Box Box 21)
  - Reston: Magazine and Newspaper Articles and Reprints, 1963-1966 (Box Box 21)
  - Reston: Reports, 1962-1967; (3 folders) (Box Box 22)
  - Reston: Research Files of William Haskett, 1961-1965 (Box Box 22)
- League of Women Voters Pamphlets
  - Carrie Chapman Catt Memorial Fund, Inc., 1951-1958 (Box Box 22)
  - Economy, 1924-1959, 1982 (Box Box 22)
  - Education, 1935-1940 (Box Box 22)
  - Government and Politics, 1923-1964 (Box Box 23)
  - League of Women Voters: History of the Organization, 1919-1983, n.d.; (4 folders) (Box Box 23)
  - Memo, 1945-1952 (Box Box 24)
  - The National Voter, 1970-1985; (2 folders) (Box Box 24)
  - Women and Children Rights, 1924-1936 (Box Box 24)
- Miscellaneous Pamphlets
  - Afro-Americans, 1933-1979, n.d. (Box Box 25)
  - Desegregation, 1959-1963 (Box Box 25)
  - Education, 1959-1963 (Box Box 25)
  - Foreign Policy, 1953 (Box Box 25)
  - Government and Politics, 1927-1986; (2 folders) (Box Box 25)
  - Government and Politics: City Management, 1949-1974 (Box Box 25)
  - Government and Politics: Virginia, 1951-1955 (Box Box 25)
  - Government and Politics: Virginia, 1964-1979 (Box Box 26)
  - Higher Education in Virginia, 1985-1987 (Box Box 26)
  - Metropolitan Washington, 1963-1976; (2 folders) (Box Box 26)
  - National American Woman Suffrage Association, 1919-1920 (Box Box 26)
  - Social Welfare, 1948-1980 (Box Box 26)
  - Status of Women, 1963-1964 (Box Box 26)
  - Status of Women, 1965 (Box Box 27)
  - Women's Issues, 1919-1988; (4 folders) (Box Box 27)
  - "Women in the Modern World," The Annals, 1929 (Box Box 27)
- Bound Volumes
  - "A Rumbling in the Museum: The Opponents of Virginia's Massive Resistance," by James Howard Hershman, Jr., 1978 (Box Box 28)
  - Leadership in a Democracy by Marguerite Milton Wells, 1944 (Box Box 28)
  - A Survey of the Legal Status of Women In the Forty-Eight States, 1930 (Box Box 28)
  - Women as Force In History by Mary R. Beard, 1946 (Box Box 28)
  - Women on their Own by Olga Knopf, 1935 (Box Box 28)
  - Women, Work, and Volunteering by Herta Loeser, 1974 (Box Box 28)
  - The History of Woman Suffrage, Vol. I, ed. by Elizabeth Cady Stanton, Susan B. Anthony, and Matilda Joslyn Gage, 1881 (Box Box 29)
  - The History of Woman Suffrage, Vol. II, ed. by Elizabeth Cady Stanton, Susan B. Anthony, and Matilda Joslyn Gage, 1881 (Box Box 29)
  - The History of Woman Suffrage, Vol. III, ed. by Elizabeth Cady Stanton, Susan B. Anthony, and Matilda Joslyn Gage, 1886 (Box Box 29)
  - The History of Woman Suffrage, Vol. V, ed. by Ida Husted Harper, 1922 (Box Box 29)
  - Political Scrapbook of Kathryn H. Stone, 1953-1955 (Box Oversize Box S-25)
- Audio Recordings
  (Transcript of reel-to-reels in Box 20 of collection)
  - Reston: Housing Conference--Parts 1 & 4, n.d.; [T-913]
  - Reston: Housing Conference--Parts 2 & 3, n.d.; [T-914]
  - Reston: Housing Conference--Parts 5 & 8, n.d.; [T-915]
  - Reston: Housing Conference--Parts 6 & 7, n.d.; [T-916]